Last year here at TED
العام الماضي هنا في تيد
I asked you to give me your data,
طلبت منكم تقديم بياناتكم،
to put your data on the web, on the basis
أن تضعوا بياناتكم على الويب، على أساس
that if people put data onto the web --
أنه إذا وضع الناس بياناتهم على الويب،
government data, scientific data, community data,
البيانات الحكومية، البيانات العلمية، البيانات المجتمعية،
whatever it is -- it will be used by other people
مهما كانت، سيستخدمها أناس آخرون
to do wonderful things, in ways
لفعل أشياء مدهشة، بطرق
that they never could have imagined.
لا يمكن تخيلها بتاتاً.
So, today I'm back just to show you a few things,
لذا، اليوم أعود فقط لأعرض عليكم القليل من الأشياء،
to show you, in fact, there is
لأعرض لكم، في الواقع، أن هناك
an open data movement afoot,
حركة بيانات مفتوحة تمضي،
now, around the world.
الآن حول العالم.
The cry of "Raw data now!"
النحيب من أجل " بيانات خام الآن،"
which I made people make in the auditorium,
الذي جعلت الناس يقومون به في القاعة،
was heard around the world.
تم سماعه حول العالم.
So, let's roll the video.
إذاً، لنقم بتشغيل الفيديو.
A classic story, the first one which lots of people picked up,
قصة كلاسيكية، الأولى التي أختارها الكثير من الناس
was when in March -- on March 10th in fact, soon after TED --
كان خلال شهر مارس، العاشر من مارس، بعد قليل من تيد،
Paul Clarke, in the U.K. government,
بول كلارك، في حكومة المملكة المتحدة
blogged, "Oh, I've just got some raw data. Here it is,
قام بتدوين، " أوه، لقد حصلت على بعض البيانات الخام. ها هي،
it's about bicycle accidents."
إنها عن حوادث الدراجات الهوائية."
Two days it took the Times Online
أستغرق الأمر يومين لتقوم صحيفة التايمز
to make a map, a mashable map --
على الإنترنت بعمل خارطة علامات تفاعلية(mashable)،
we call these things mash-ups --
نسمي هذه الأشياء علامات تفاعلية،
a mashed-up user interface that allows you to go in there
العلامة، واجهة مستخدم تسمح لك بالذهاب هناك
and have a look and find out whether your bicycle
وإلقاء نظرة لمعرفة ما إذا كان طريق
route to work was affected.
دراجتك الى العمل قد تأثّر.
Here's more data, traffic survey data,
هناك مزيد من البيانات، إستطلاعات حركة المرور،
again, put out by the U.K. government,
مجدداً، تم وضعها من قبل حكومة المملكة المتحدة،
and because they put it up using the Linked Data standards,
ولأنهم وضعوها بمعايير البيانات المترابطة
then a user could just make a map,
عندئذ بمستطاع المستخدم صنع خارطة،
just by clicking.
بمجرد النقر عليها.
Does this data affect things? Well, let's get back to 2008.
هذا تؤثر هذه البيانات في شئ؟ حسناً لنرجع لعام 2008.
Look at Zanesville, Ohio.
أنظروا في زانسفيلي، أوهايو.
Here's a map a lawyer made. He put on it the water plant,
ها هي خارطة إنشأها محامي، وضعها في محطة مياة،
and which houses are there,
ليرى أي المنازل هناك،
which houses have been connected to the water.
أي المنازل تم توصيل الماء إليها؟
And he got, from other data sources,
وقد توصل، من مصادر بيانات أخرى،
information to show
على معلومات تعرض
which houses are occupied by white people.
أي المنازل يسكنها سكان بيض.
Well, there was too much of a correlation, he felt,
حسناً، لقد كان هناك الكثير من الترابط، كما أحس هو،
between which houses were occupied by white people
بين أي المنازل يسكنها أناس بيض
and which houses had water, and the judge was not impressed either.
وأي المنازل موصولة بالماء، وحتى القاضي لم يكن مندهشاً.
The judge was not impressed to the tune of 10.9 million dollars.
القاضي لم يكن مندهشاً للحكم ب 10.9 مليون دولار.
That's the power of taking one piece of data,
هذه هي قوة أخذ قطعة واحدة من البيانات،
another piece of data, putting it together,
وقطعة أخرى من البيانات، ووضعهم سوياً،
and showing the result.
وعرض النتائج.
Let's look at some data from the U.K. now.
لنأخذ نظرة على بعض البيانات من المملكة المتحدة الآن.
This is U.K. government data, a completely independent site,
بيانات الحكومة الإنجليزية، من موقع مستقل تماماً،
Where Does My Money Go.
أين تذهب أموالي،
It allows anybody to go there and burrow down.
يسمحون لأي شخص بالذهاب هناك وتحفر للأسفل.
You can burrow down by a particular type of spending,
يمكنك الغوص لأسفل بنوع محدد من الإنفاق
or you can go through all the different regions and compare them.
أو يمكنك الإستكشاف عبر كل المناطق المختلفة وتقوم بمقارنتها.
So, that's happening in the U.K. with U.K. government data.
لذا، هذا يحدث في المملكة المتحدة مع بيانات الحكومة الإنجليزية.
Yes, certainly you can do it over here.
نعم، بالتأكيد يمكنك فعل ذلك هنا.
Here's a site which allows you to look at recovery spending
ها هي موقع يسمح لك بالنظر على إنفاق الإنعاش الإقتصادي
in California.
في كاليفورنيا.
Take an arbitrary example, Long Beach, California,
وخذ مثالاً تعسفياً، لونغ بيتش، كالفورنيا،
you can go and have a look at what recovery money they've been spending
يمكنك الذهاب والنظر على أي أموال الإنعاش الإقتصادي تم صرفها
on different things such as energy.
على مختلف الأشياء مثل الطاقة.
In fact, this is the graph of the number of data sets
في الحقيقة، هذا هو رسم بياني لعدد من مجموعات البيانات
in the repositories of data.gov,
في مخازن البيانات data.gov،
and data.gov.uk.
و data.gov.uk.
And I'm delighted to see a great competition
وأنا مسرور لرؤية المنافسة العظيمة
between the U.K. in blue, and the U.S. in red.
بين المملكة المتحدة في الأزرق، والولايات المتحدة في الأحمر.
How can you use this stuff?
كيف يمكننا إستخدام هذه الأشياء؟
Well, for example, if you have lots of data about places
حسناً، كمثال، إذا تحصلت على الكثير من البيانات حول الأماكن
you can take, from a postcode --
يمكنك أخذ، من الرمز البريدي،
which is like a zip plus four --
التي مثل الرمز زائد أربعة،
for a specific group of houses, you can make paper,
لمجموعة محددة من المنازل، يمكنك إنشاء ورقة،
print off a paper which has got very, very
وطباعتها الشئ الذي لديه
specific things about the bus stops,
أشياء محددة جداً جداً حول مواقف الباصات،
the things specifically near you.
والأشياء القريبة منك تحديداً.
On a larger scale, this is a mash-up
المستوى الكبير، هذه هي خارطة
of the data which was released about the Afghan elections.
للبيانات التي نشرت عن الإنتخابات الأفغانية.
It allows you to set your own criteria
إنها تسمح لك بوضع طريقتك الخاصة
for what sort of things you want to look at.
لأي نوع من الأشياء تريد النظر إليه.
The red circles are polling stations,
الدوائر الحمراء هي مراكز الإقتراع،
selected by your criteria.
مُختارة بواسطة طريقتك الخاصة.
And then you can select also other things on the map
ثم يمكنك إختيار أشياء أخرى على الخارطة
to see what other factors, like the threat level.
لرؤية ما هي العوامل الأخرى مثل مستوى التهديد.
So, that was government data.
إذاً، كانت تلك بيانات الحكومة.
I also talked about community-generated data -- in fact I edited some.
تحدثت كذلك عن البيانات المنتجة بواسطة المجتمعات - لقد حررت--
This is the wiki map, this is the Open Street Map.
هذه الخارطة الويكي، ها هي خارطة الشارع المفتوحة.
"Terrace Theater" I actually put
مسرح تيراس، لقد وضعتها
on the map because it wasn't on the map before TED last year.
على الخارطة لأنها لم تكن على الخارطة قبل مؤتمر تيد في العام الماضي.
I was not the only person editing the open street map.
لم أكن الوحيد الذي يحرر خارطة الشارع المفتوحة.
Each flash on this visualization --
كل ومضة على هذا التصوير
put together by ITO World --
وضعت سوياً بواسطة منظمة التجارة الدولية
shows an edit in 2009
تعرض تحريراً في 2009
made to the Open Street Map.
صُنعت لخارطة الشارع المفتوحة.
Let's now spin the world during the same year.
لنقم الآن بتدوير العالم خلال نفس السنة.
Every flash is an edit. Somebody somewhere
كل ومضة هي تحرير. شخص ما في مكان ما
looking at the Open Street Map, and realizing it could be better.
ينظر على خارطة الشارع المفتوحة، وأدرك إنها يمكن أن تتحسن.
You can see Europe is ablaze with updates.
يمكنكم رؤية أوروبا تشتعل مع التحديثات.
Some places, perhaps not as much as they should be.
بعض الأماكن، ربما ليست كما ينبغي أن تكون.
Here focusing in on Haiti.
ها هو تركيز على هاييتي.
The map of Port au-Prince at the end
هذه خارطة بورت أو برينس في نهاية
of 2009 was not all it could be,
عام 2009 لم تكن كما يمكن أن تكون،
not as good as the map of California.
ليست جيدة مثل خارطة كالفورنيا.
Fortunately, just after the earthquake,
لحسن الحظ، تماماً بعد الزلزال،
GeoEye, a commercial company,
شركة GeoEye، التجارية،
released satellite imagery
نشرت صور الأقمار الصناعية
with a license, which allowed
بترخيص الذي أتاح
the open-source community to use it.
لمجتمع المصادر المفتوحة بإستخدامها.
This is January, in time lapse,
هذا هو الفاصل الزمني في يناير،
of people editing ... that's the earthquake.
الناس يحررون، ذلك هو الزلزال.
After the earthquake, immediately,
بعد الزلزال في الحال
people all over the world, mappers
الناس من كل العالم، راسمو الخرط
who wanted to help, and could,
الذين أرادوا المساعدة، وإستطاعوا،
looked at that imagery, built the map, quickly building it up.
نظروا على تلك الصور، وبنوا خارطة، وبنوا بسرعة.
We're focusing now on Port-au-Prince.
نحن نركز الآن، على بورت أو برينس.
The light blue is refugee camps these volunteers had spotted from the [satellite images].
بالأزرق هي مخيمات اللاجئين التي ألتقطها المتطوعون من الجو.
So, now we have, immediately, a real-time map
إذاً، لدينا الآن، خارطة فورية
showing where there are refugee camps --
تعرض أين هي مخيمات اللاجئين هذه،
rapidly became the best map
بسرعة تصبح أفضل الخرائط
to use if you're doing relief work in Port-au-Prince.
لتستخدم إذا كنت تقوم بجهود المساعدات في بورت أو برينس.
Witness the fact that it's here on this Garmin device
أشهدوا على حقيقة أن جهاز غارمين يُستخدم
being used by rescue team in Haiti.
بواسطة فرق الإنقاذ.
There's the map showing,
وهاييتي، هناك خارطة تعرض
on the left-hand side,
على الجانب الأيسر هناك،
that hospital -- actually that's a hospital ship.
ذلك مستشفى، في الواقع تلك رقاقة مستشفى.
This is a real-time map that shows blocked roads,
هذه خارطة فورية تعرض الطرق المغلقة
damaged buildings, refugee camps --
المباني المدمرة، مخيمات اللاجئين.
it shows things that are needed [for rescue and relief work].
إنها تعرض الأشياء التي تحتاجها.
So, if you've been involved in that at all,
لذا، إذا كنت مشارك في ذلك كلياً،
I just wanted to say: Whatever you've been doing,
أردت فقط القول إنه مهما ما كنت تفعله،
whether you've just been chanting, "Raw data now!"
سواء كنت تقوم برسم بياني للبيانات الخام الآن،
or you've been putting government or scientific data online,
أو كنت تضع البيانات الحكومية أو العلمية على الإنترنت،
I just wanted to take this opportunity to say: Thank you very much,
رغبت فقط أن أنتهز هذه الفرصة لأقول شكراً جزيلاً لكم،
and we have only just started!
ولقد بدأنا للتو.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)